<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Technology | Alex Kyllo]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexkyllo.com/blog/categories/technology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexkyllo.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-06T21:41:33-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexkyllo.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Kyllo]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breathing Through Tubes]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexkyllo.com/blog/2013/04/06/breathing-through-tubes/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-06T19:58:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexkyllo.com/blog/2013/04/06/breathing-through-tubes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ll start this post off with a quote that inspired it, from Paul Graham&rsquo;s 2012 essay <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/property.html">Defining Property</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The record labels and movie studios used to distribute what they made like air shipped through tubes on a moon base. But with the
arrival of networks, it&rsquo;s as if we&rsquo;ve moved to a planet with a breathable atmosphere. Data moves like smells now. And through a
combination of wishful thinking and short-term greed, the labels and studios have put themselves in the position of the food shop
owner, accusing us all of stealing their smells.</p></blockquote>

<p>By comparing digital data to air, and comparing songs and movies to smells emanating from a restaurant, Graham is making the point that it just doesn&rsquo;t work to charge for copies of media content anymore, at least without &ldquo;warping society&rdquo; by successfully lobbying for laws that force us to use obsolete technology. &ldquo;Companies selling smells on the moon base could continue to sell them on the Earth, if they lobbied successfully for laws requiring us all to continue to breathe through tubes down here too, even though we no longer needed to,&rdquo; says Graham. And that is exactly what the MPAA and RIAA have done with the DMCA (Digital Millenium Copyright Act).</p>

<p>Since I read this essay, I&rsquo;ve been thinking intellectual property (IP) in the tech economy in a broader sense for a while now, and the overwhelming feeling I get is that our system is not just flawed, but <em>broken</em>. Finding a reasonable and equitable solution to this problem is going to be major challenge and a test of our society, as property rights are a key component of the &ldquo;grand bargain&rdquo; in which we all participate as a society.</p>

<p>Now, we&rsquo;ve all known about the filesharing debate since Napster, (then its clones like Kazaa, Morpheus, Limewire), and later, BitTorrent. The RIAA and MPAA were victorious in having peer-to-peer sharing of digital representations of copyrighted works declared illegal and file-sharers selectively punished with six-figure fines to make an example of them. Yet this was somewhat of a pyrrhic victory as it made these organizations widely reviled by their own customers. Napster et al were forced to innovate in order to stay above-board, so they pivoted and negotiated licensing deals to become paid subscription services. With newer entrants like Pandora and Spotify experiencing success, this is now a proven business model. Meanwhile Hulu, Netflix and others are doing the same for movies and TV. People may not be willing to pay high per-file costs for digital copies, but they are willing to pay for convenience of having content easily streamed to any device. And although these services are legal and properly licensed, it is important to remember that the content owners fought tooth-and-nail to suppress them. They are still fighting further innovations to protect their profits, only giving in to each new technology when it becomes truly inevitable. Therefore the &ldquo;cutting edge&rdquo; in this market is always outside the law, and this has a chilling effect on innovation. Meanwhile these organizations continue to lobby to introduce legislation like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop_Online_Piracy_Act">SOPA</a> to grant themselves the power to censor the internet and expand criminal penalties for sharing copyrighted data.</p>

<p>In addition to legal threats and censorship, another strategy that content owners use to protect their copyrights is by using DRM (Digital Rights Management), a catchall name for anti-copying encryption software. Of course this sparked a bit of an arms race, as each time they implement a new DRM system, users always find a way to crack it. So they have had to make cracking the code illegal as well. This led to a less-publicized but still very important copyright battle in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DeCSS">DeCSS</a> affair, which led to a criminal trial in Norway, along with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AACS_encryption_key_controversy">AACS encryption key controversy</a>, which provoked the MPAA and AACS to serve many websites with DMCA demand notices. These incidents involved people sharing source code and encryption keys for cracking HD-DVD players, represented as hexadecimal numbers, giving rise to the concept of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illegal_number">Illegal numbers</a>. The concept is that since <em>any</em> information, including executable computer programs and copyrighted content, can be represented as a number, some numbers are themselves secret and protected by copyright, making them illegal to distribute or even to possess. That&rsquo;s right, the number 99,206,706,771,272,430,000 for example is <em>contraband</em>. Users correctly saw this as a threat to free speech, and in response to attempted censorship, they spread it and other &ldquo;illegal numbers&rdquo; all over the internet, to the point where they were impossible to contain. Meanwhile the DRM encryption arms race continues, most recently with the attempt to introduce DRM into the HTML5 standard. <a href="http://www.engadget.com/2012/02/23/google-microsoft-and-netflix-want-drm-like-encryption-in-html5/">This particular effort is even being backed by Google, Microsoft and Netflix.</a> For shame.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been picking on organizations like the RIAA and MPAA, but they are not the only ones who work to expand and abuse IP rights for profit. The most recent and blatant misuse of IP to suppress technological innovation, and make a fast buck in the process, is the phenomenon of &ldquo;patent trolls.&rdquo; Joel Spolsky gives <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/items/2013/04/02.html">a great, brief explanation of what they are and how they are running a high-tech, legal protection racket.</a> These people have made lucrative careers of setting up shell companies, acquiring overly broad, nearly expired tech patents and abusing them to threaten actual productive companies with costly litigation if they refuse to pay their extortionate &ldquo;licensing&rdquo; fees. I do not think these trolls will last much longer, as they are now broadly reviled and have raised the ire of major Silicon Valley companies, who are starting to fight back in court and win. Judges also seem unsupportive of these trolls, if <a href="http://www.popehat.com/tag/prenda-law/">the Prenda Law case as documented at popehat.com</a> is any evidence.</p>

<p>While for the time being, there&rsquo;s basically nothing an innovative company can do to avoid drive-by litigation threats from patent trolls, on the other hand one can, with a crack legal team and a little ingenuity, find big enough loopholes in the outdated IP laws to fit a business model through. Don&rsquo;t you think that in the future, we will all eventually be watching our live TV over the internet instead of via cable? Well <a href="https://www.aereo.com/">Aereo</a> is offering that now&ndash;and not only can you watch the content live, you can also &ldquo;record&rdquo; it to watch later as you would with a DVR. Now, what is the the difference between this and downloading the content from a file-sharing service? Conceptually, almost nothing. But due to a technicality in the law, <a href="http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2013/04/appeals-court-upholds-legality-of-aereos-tiny-antennas-scheme/">the legality of their business model was upheld in court</a>, at least for now. Here&rsquo;s how the scheme works:</p>

<blockquote><p>In Aereo&rsquo;s server rooms are row after row of tiny antennas mounted on circuit boards. When a user wants to view or record a
television program, Aereo assigns him an antenna exclusively for his own use. And like Cablevision, when 1000 users record the
same program, Aereo creates 1,000 redundant copies.</p></blockquote>

<p>Tiny antennas&hellip; redundant copies&hellip; right. Now there is obviously no technical reason at all why it would be necessary to have thousands of redundant copies of the same content in their data center, and install one tiny antenna per customer, just to serve TV show files over the internet. But the fact that no two customers are &ldquo;sharing&rdquo; the same copy of the show is the only reason why their business model isn&rsquo;t legally considered copyright infringement. It will be very interesting to see what happens with Aereo&ndash;whether the loophole they&rsquo;ve found for themselves will be forced open wider, or whether the much larger and wealthier content distributors will find a way to use the legal system to sew it shut.</p>

<p>Originally, copyrights, trademarks, and other legal IP protections were conceived in order to encourage innovation and artistic expression by preventing someone else from misappropriating one&rsquo;s creative work as their own. Patents were designed to give inventors a head start by affording them a <em>temporary</em> monopoly on selling the technology they invented, in order to prevent a competitor from copying their invention and bringing it to market faster.</p>

<p>But what these IP protections are actually being used for, is to entrench profitable business models, and stifle competition in order to perpetuate rent-seeking behavior. See, in an efficient economy, no business can stay profitable for long without innovating, because competiting actors will use technological progress to introduce products that are incrementally better and cheaper, until your product is totally obsolete. The only way to stop that from happening, at least temporarily, is by protecting your business model with patents and copyrights, and threatening costly litigation. This is how record companies and movie studios are still able to make a fortune selling their entertainment on spinning disks, which are otherwise thoroughly obsolete. To borrow Graham&rsquo;s analogy, they are forcing us to breathe through tubes by making it illegal to breathe the air freely, so that they can continue to charge for smells.</p>

<p>I am starting to believe that weakening copyrights and patents, and strengthening our right to freely disseminate information, is a key part of how we are going to make the future more economically equitable than the present. By misusing the legal system to expand intellectual property rights and protect their profitable business models from disruptive tech innovation, these companies are exacerbating the inequitable distribution of wealth in our society. Fighting to defend our free speech rights and expand &ldquo;fair use&rdquo; protections is an important way that we are going to enable ourselves to all use technology to create wealth for ourselves and share it with each other. (Remember that wealth does not mean &ldquo;money,&rdquo; but much more generally, anything people want.)</p>

<p>The most common criticism of anti-copyright beliefs is that they are merely a thin justification for freeloading. But really, what harm is &ldquo;freeloading&rdquo; a non-exclusive good? Copying is <em>not</em> the same as stealing (or &ldquo;piracy,&rdquo; which means using violence to steal). Copying doesn&rsquo;t actually cost anyone else anything nor deprive anyone else of the ability to enjoy the information being copied. The claim that copying is depriving the content owner of the revenue equivalent to the price they charge for a copy of the media, is only valid if you accept the assertion that a copyright is and should be a perpetual, exclusive (but transferrable, for a price) license to distribute copies of a piece of information. I reject such an assertion, as that is very far from what copyrights were ever intended to be.</p>

<p>Now, if copyrights are weakened to the point that file sharing becomes legal (which I think is inevitable), I don&rsquo;t claim to know exactly what will happen to movie studios, record companies, publishing houses, etc. if technology makes it impossible to continue under their current business model of acquiring the exclusive right to sell individual copies of artists' work. But I am confident that if society values blockbuster motion pictures, smash-hit songs, and bestseller novels, we will find a way to pay for them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
